Inventory of the Jerdone Family Papers 1753-1890, 1771-1845
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Miscellaneous Material (Box-folder 13:1-9)
  - Jerdone Family Data File, 1720-1833, n.d. (Box-folder 13:1)
    - Tombstone inscriptions for Francis Jerdone [1720-1771], Mary Jerdone [1781-1821] and James Jerdone [1812-1827], n.d. (Box-folder 13:1)
    - Handwritten plat of burial plot made by John Jerdone for Francis Jerdone Sr., showing enlarged burial plot and proposed order of burial, n.d., 1 page. Ms. (Box-folder 13:1)
    - Photograph of Jedburgh, n.d., 1 item. Ph. Black and White. 7 1/4" x 11" (Box-folder 13:1)
    - Newspaper clipping about Frank Jerdone and mementoes of his aviation career, 23 September 1957., 1 page. NCl. (Box-folder 13:1)
  - Photographs, of a portrait of Francis Jerdone II and of a family record, along with correspondence between the owner of the portrait, Mrs. R.C. Marthinson and James A. Servies, Librarian of the College of William and Mary, n.d., 7 items. Ph. TCy of LS and ALS. Black and White. 8" x 10" (Box-folder 13:2)
  - Miscellaneous papers arranged by author. 1749-1918. (Box-folder 13:3)
    Arranged in alphabetical order by author.
    - Burfitt [M. M.]., 11 pages. MS. (Box-folder 13:3)
      Notes of the late war not contained in reports of the generals, by M. M. Burfitt, at Providence Forge, New Kent County, Virginia Refers to the American Civil War, particularly the Battle of Bethel.
    - Coleman [Miriam], 1914-1918., 4 pages. MS. (Box-folder 13:3)
      What the big guns eat. An English theme by Miriam Coleman. Written during the European War 1914-1918.
    - Jerdone [Alexander]., 3 pages. (Box-folder 13:3)
      Poetry and pencil sketches by Alexander Jerdone.
    - Jerdone [John], 1810-1811., 2 items. (Box-folder 13:3)
      School copy book of John Jerdone. 1811. 46 pages. AMSV.
      Page of copy book of 26 November 1810. 4 pages. AMsV.
    - Jerdone [William], 1813., 32 pages. AMsV. (Box-folder 13:3)
      School copy book of William Jerdone.
    - MacFarland [William], 16 June 1749., 1 page. DS. (Box-folder 13:3)
      Extract of the will of William MacFarland, of London [England], leaving his property to his sister, Mrs. Catherine Scott.
    - Mercer [?], a physician., 2 pages. Ms. (Box-folder 13:3)
      Course of treatment prescribed by Dr. Mercer for a child with a bad lax.
    - Myrick [Robert]. 25 June 1832., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 13:3)
      Letter of recommendation of Robert Myrick as overseer.
    - Thompson [David] estate, 12 January 1749., 2 pages. DS. (Box-folder 13:3)
      Appraisement of the estate of David Thompson.
    - Willis [Francis], 1768., 2 pages. D. (Box-folder 13:3)
      List of bonds payable to Francis Willis delivered to John Hawkins to be collected by him.
    - Embroidery design., 1 page. Ms. (Box-folder 13:3)
    - Verses and mottoes., 4 items. (Box-folder 13:3)
    - Memorandum book containing definitions of words., 21 pages. MsV. (Box-folder 13:3)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1798, n.d. (Box-folder 13:4)
    - Sketch of leg and foot measurements, J. Didsbury, boot and shoemaker, London., 1 page. Engraving. (Box-folder 13:4)
      Note: The royal coat of arms appears on this sheet.
    - The Cape of Good Hope, n.d., 1 page. Engracing. (Box-folder 13:4)
      1 engraving from the London Magazine. 1754.
    - The University of Virginia, n.d., 1 page. Engraving. (Box-folder 13:4)
    - Monthly army list of Great Britain, London, 1 February 1798., 84 pages. 1 printed pamphlet. (Box-folder 13:4)
    - Miscellaneous printed material., 7 items. (Box-folder 13:4)
    - Unidentified material and Fragments., 18 items. (Box-folder 13:4)
    - Labels and covers taken from the original bundles of papers in this collection., 9 items. (Box-folder 13:4)
  - Xerox copies of typescripts from the James Murray Letterbook, New York Historical Society Library, 1733-1735., 19 TCys. (Box-folder 13:5)
    - Xerox copies of typescripts of Pages 78-82, 6 October 1733. (Box-folder 13:5)
      Murray to Chesters, page 81 mentions Baillie Jeardon [father of Francis Jerdone I].
    - Xerox copies of typescripts of Pages 121-122, 17 September 1734. (Box-folder 13:5)
      Murray to Chesters, page 121 mentions Mr. Jardon.
    - Xerox copies of typescripts of Pages 131-134, 26 October 1734. (Box-folder 13:5)
      Murray to Chesters, page 141 refers to Bailie Jardon.
    - Xerox copies of typescripts of Pages 149-150, 15 April 1735. (Box-folder 13:5)
      Murray to Chesters, page 149 refers to Franc Jerdon.
    - Xerox copies of typescripts of Page 150, 19 April 1735. (Box-folder 13:5)
      Murray to Baillie Jerdon, concerning his son Francis Jerdone's apprenticeship to Neill Buchanan.
    - Xerox copies of typescripts of Pages 157-160, 17 May 1735. (Box-folder 13:5)
      Murray to Baillie Jerdon, concerning his son Francis Jerdone.
  - Copies of Jerdone family records from family Bibles, 16 pages. Cys of Mss. (Box-folder 13:6)
    Includes photograph of portrait, 3 1/2" x 3 1/2", black and white, of John Jerdone, son of Francis Jerdone, 3rd. Ph. and negative. 2 items.
  - Newspaper clippings about Jerdone homes, "Jerdone Castle.", 3 items. NCl. (Box-folder 13:7)
  - Typescripts about Bloomsbury and Colonel James Taylor., 2 items. Tcys. (Box-folder 13:8)
  - Framed colored photograph of newspaper picturing Jerdone Castle., Ph. Color. 11 3/4" x 14 3/4". (Box-folder 13:9)
  Series 6: Manuscript Volumes
- Manuscript Volumes (Box 14-16)
  Series 6 is arranged alphabetically by individual's last name.
  - Jerdone, (Anna Thornton Burfitt), 1844-1866, n.d. (Volume MsV. 1-5)
    - Notebook containing an analysis of Lord Henry Home Kames' Elements of Criticism, made by Anna Thornton Burfitt, while a student at [Troy Female Seminary, Troy, New York], 1844., 134 pages. 8 1/4 x 7 inches. (Volume MsV. 1)
    - Notebook containing an analysis of Dugald Stewart's Philosophy of the active and moral powers of man, made by Anna Thornton Burfitt, while a student at the Troy Female Seminary, Troy, New York, 1844-1845., 146 pages. 8 1/4 x 6 3/4 inches. (Volume MsV. 2)
    - Notebook containing an analysis of Dugald Stewart's Elements of the Philosophy of the Human Mind, made by Anna Thornton Burfitt, while a student at Troy Female Seminary, Troy, New York., 168 pages. 8 x 7 inches. (Volume MsV. 3)
      Volume 1.
    - Notebook containing an analysis of Dugald Stewart's Elements of the Philosophy of the Human Mind, made by Anna Thornton Burfitt, while a student at Troy Female Seminary, Troy, New York., 154 pages. 8 1/4 x 7 inches. (Volume MsV. 4)
      Volume 2.
    - Notebook of Anna B. Jerdone, second wife of William Jerdone, containing poetry, comments, copies of letters, and recipes, 1847-1866., 44 pages. 10 1/4 x 8 inches. (Volume MsV. 5)
  - Jerdone, (Francis), 1721-1771. (Volume MsV. 6-15)
    - Account book of Francis Jerdone, 1750-1752., 280 pages. 16 x 6 1/2 inches. Covered with parchment. (Volume MsV. 6)
    - Account book of the mercantile business of Francis Jerdone, 1750-1772., 740 pages. 18 1/2 x 13 1/2 inches. (Volume MsV. 7)
    - Account and letterbook containing accounts, 1736-1737; and copies of letters written by William Johnston and Francis Jerdone, 1738-1744; 1736-1744., 376 pages. 16 x 7 inches. Laminated July 1955 by W. J. Barrow. (Volume MsV. 8)
      Jerdone's predecessor as factor for Buchanan & Hamilton was William Johnston. Jerdone evidently came to Virginia to replace Johnston in September 1740.
    - Letter copybook of Francis Jerdone, 1756-1763., 268 pages. 13 1/4 x 8 1/2 inches. Laminated July 1955 by W.J. Barrow. (Volume MsV. 9)
      Also includes a record of tobacco shipped prior to 1759.
    - Daybook of Francis Jerdone, 1752-1759. (Volume MsV. 10)
    - Account book of Francis Jerdone, merchant in Hanover County, 1743-1745., 256 pages. 19 3/4 x 8 1/4 inches. (Volume MsV. 11)
  - Jerdone [Francis], 1756-1841. (Volume 12-15)
    - Arithmetic workbook of Francis Jerdone, 1770-1773., 10 1/2 x 8 1/2 inches. (Volume MsV. 12)
    - Diary of Francis Jerdone in two volumes, 24 April 1834-17 June 1840., 368 pages. 13 x 8 1/2 inches. (Volume MsV. 13)
      Volume 1 concerns agriculture, daily life and slavery.
    - Diary of Francis Jerdone in two volumes, 17 June 1840-14 April 1841., 64 pages. 12 3/4 x 8 1/4 inches. (Volume MsV. 14)
      Volume 2 concerns agriculture, daily life and slavery, and also some poetry and recipes.
  - Jerdone, (Francis), 1856-1863., 3 3/4 x 6 inches. (Volume MsV. 15)
    Account book of Francis Jerdone, Orange County, Virginia. First leaf contains note of payment of tuition at the College of William and Mary for his son John, a student there, 1855-1856.
  - Jordan (John Morton) and Company, 1769-1776., 235 pages. 13 1/4 x 8 1/4 inches. (Volume MsV. 16)
    Letterbook containing copies of letters written by Thomas Jett, the Virginia representative of John Morton Jordan and Co., and of Perkins, Buchanan and Brown, merchants in London, England.
    Correspondents include John Anderson, John Backhouse, Messrs Barlow, Wigginton, Francis & Holland of London, England, James Bowles, Messrs. Clay & Miogley of Liverpool, England, Nisbett, Darby, William Gibson, Samuel Gist, Messrs. Hanson, Clark & Co. of London, England, Henry Holland, Richard Humphreys, Mrs. Dorothy Jordan, John Morton Jordan, John Morton Jordan & Co. of London, England, Thomas Jarvis, William Lee, Dr. Michael McNemara, Messrs. McNemara & Jennings, Robert Maxwell, Thomas Oswala, William Perkins, Perkins, Buchanan & Brown of London, England, William Quinny, Stevenson, Randolph & Co. of Bristol, Messrs. Talte, Alexander & Co. of London, England, Mrs. Francis Ward, Thomas Ward, Messrs. Willimott, Brooks, & Lafant, and Messrs. Willson & R. Mollison of London, England.
    For other information concerning J. M. Morton & Company and on Perkins, Buchanan and Brown see the Thomas Adams Papers in the Virginia Historical Society.
  - Jerdone (William), 1834-1877. (Volume MsV. 17-21)
    - Journal of William Jerdone's transactions, 1834-1847., 107 pages. 13 1/2 x 8 1/2 inches. (Volume MsV. 17)
    - Day book of William Jerdone, containing accounts of the Forge Estate held in partnership by Francis Jerdone, Jr., and William Jerdone, 1832-1835., 54 pages. 12 1/4 x 8 inches. (Volume MsV. 18)
      Also includes sketches written by William M. Jerdone at Virginia Military Institute, 1870-1871.
    - Diaries of William Jerdone, 1861-1867., 166 pages. 14 x 8 3/4 inches. (Volume MsV. 19)
      Diary of William Jerdone, 1861-1862; and diary of William M. Jerdone, 1863-1867. Diaries concern agriculture, preparation for war, home front, managing slaves, reconstruction, and military defenses at Jamestown, Williamsburg, and Yorktown.
    - Journal of transactions between William M. Jerdone and various persons, 1866-1877., 126 pages. 13 1/4 x 8 1/4 inches. (Volume MsV. 20)
    - Memorandum book of William Jerdone, 1855-1863. (Volume MsV. 21)
      Book contains farm records, records of doctors' visits, records of produce and animals stolen, hiring of a free black, record of slaves working on public defenses at Jamestown and the beginning of a diary continued in MsV. 19 of William M. Jerdone, Jr.
  Series 7: Artifacts
- Artifacts, 1800-1889, n.d. (Box 17-19)
  - Homespun tablecloth, identified as belonging to the grandmother of Mrs. Lilly Robinson Jerdone. Spottsylvania County [?], circa 1800 [?]. (Box 17)
    Descriptive notes by Mrs. Davis are attached.
  - Two hand-embroidered chemises, identified verbally by Mrs. Davis as having belonged to her grandmother, Circa 1860.
  - Velvet covered Jewelry box, Mrs. Davis notes that it was given to Miss Eliza Mayo Jerdone by her father, John Jerdone, when she was a little girl, over 75 years ago, [1889?], Box contains 6 items. 7 1/2" x 4 3/4" x 2 1/2". (Box 18)
    The box also contains the following items:
    1. Button hook
    2. Thimble
    3. Tie pin, made of a toothpick case [cover lacking]
    4. Copper medalion, oval, about 3" x 2 1/4", in cloth case The following message is engraved on the Facet "How lov'd How valued once avails thee not. / Mary Jerdone died March 12th 1821 / Sarah Jerdone died October 23rd 1818." Evidently contained a miniature, not received with this gift.
    5. Silk crepe bow, identified as once belonging to Mrs. Davis' mother, Lilly Robinson Jerdone.
    6. Various descriptive notes made by Mrs. Davis regarding the above items.
  - Old leather basket, owned by Mrs. Davis' grandmother, Eliza Mayo Jerdone. (Box 18)
    Also contains a pewter container, identified as an old "powder and shot flask." Mrs. Davis' notes describing these items are also laid in.
  - Brown glasses case. (Box 18)
  - Philomathean pin, 1852. (Box 18)
  - Pearl change purse which belonged to Mrs. Francis Jerdone III. (Box 18)
  - Walking cane. (Box 18)
  - Glasses with monogram GHW., 2 items. 5 1/2" high (Box 19)
  - Pewter candle holder for two candles., 4" high. (Box 19)
  - Cast iron bell., 3 1/2" high. (Box 19)
  - Silver-plated cup., 3 3/4" high. (Box 19)
    See descriptive note attached.
  - Bureau toilet set, owned by Mrs. Davis' mother, Lily Robinson Jerdone, Circa 1875., 3 items. 3-6 1/2" high. (Box 19)
  Series 8: Additions and Accessions to the Collection
- Additions and Accessions to the Collection, 1746-1775, n.d.
  Includes the following four additions and accessions to the collection:
  Acc. No. 83-64
  Mss. Sm. Coll. Add. 17
  Mss. 1997.45
  Mss. 1998.7
  - Accession to the collection, Acc. No. 83-64, n.d., 1 page. MS. (Box-folder 13:1)
    Penciled genealogy chart showing ancestry of Francis and Sarah [Macon] Jerdone down through their descendants to the Colemans.
  - Addition to the collection, Mss. Sm. Coll. Add. 17, 1775, n.d., 4 items. (Othertype Mss. Sm. Coll. Add. 17)
    - Petition of Sarah Jerdone, widow of Francis Jerdone, "To the honourable the Speaker & Gentlemen of the House of Delegates," [1775?]., 2 pages. Photostat of draft of D. (Othertype Mss. Sm. Coll. Add. 17)
      Argues in behalf of her sons Francis and John who are in England and their land in Virginia is found by inquest to be subject to escheat and forfeiture under the last Act of Assembly concerning escheats and forfeitures from British subjects.
    - Hartwell Genealogy., 1 page. Copy. (Othertype Mss. Sm. Coll. Add. 17)
    - Macon Genealogy., 3 pages. Copy. (Othertype Mss. Sm. Coll. Add. 17)
    - Jerdone Family Bible Record., 2 pages. Copy. (Othertype Mss. Sm. Coll. Add. 17)
  - Addition to the collection, Mss. 1997.45, 1746-1757., 3 items. (Othertype Mss. 1997.45)
    - Invoice book of Francis Jerdone of King and Queen County, Virginia, 1746-1757., 179 pages. Microfilm required. 15 7/8 x 6 1/4 inches. (Volume MsV. 22)
    - Ledger of Francis Jerdone of King and Queen County, Virginia, 1748-1750., 259 pages. Filmed. 14 3/4 x 91/8 inches. (Volume MsV. 23)
    - Index, 1750 to Ledger B., 30 pages. 15 x 9 1/3 inches. (Volume MsV. 24)
      Ledger B is not included.
  - Addition to the collection, Mss. 1998.7, n.d., 2 items. (Othertype Mss. 1998.7)
    - Genealogical notes of Francis Jerdone's family. (Folder 1)
      Also included are copies of wills, deeds, and recollections of the Jerdone castle.
    - Copy of a portrait of Francis Jerdone II and copy of the bill from R. N. Sully to William Jerdone for painting a portrait of his father. (Folder 2)